thank you so much I'm very excited I'm
thankful to get an opportunity to speak
on this topic I've these days mostly
been talking about education and
educational systems and their role and
when I characterize as a global
meta-crisis and so I've been talking a
lot about education because of this
forthcoming book but in this book
there's a chapter which I think it's
actually maybe the best one if I can say
that and it's a it's about measurement
it's about a measurement as a global
issue and really about the uniqueness of
our historical moment from the
perspective of the evolution of
consciousness so I'm gonna talk about
I'm gonna talk a lot about that but to
pick up on what was just mentioned so I
came to this topic of measurement which
is very abstract and weird in fact like
I geek out on ancient Sumerian staffs
that have marks on them which were some
of the first measurement and I geeked
out on the most ancient forms of you
know sacred architecture which were fact
artifacts used to codify time you know
through this through structure that
responded to the changes in the Sun etc
and so but I came know this from
educational measurement
you know I'm Dyslexic and so I was
consistently mismeasured or felt to be
and I realize that measurement is an
invisible part of our day-to-day lives
in fact if you sit there and you think
about the number of ways you understand
yourself through the prism of a measure
it is in fact hard to end the
enumeration of the list and many of
these things are in fact very recent so
people don't realize that the use of
number to mark our chronological age
it's something that did not begin on a
wide scale until after the Civil War so
that's less than 200 years ago it used
to be you were the helvis you're the
youngest
born before after this major historical
marker so to the flood but the knowledge
and the need to know your exact
numerical age let alone your precise
birthday you know that's an artifact of
our bureaucracy age is one of those
things the number we apply ourselves to
measure chronological time wait is
another one there's a very direct
correlation between the availability of
the bathroom scale the mass-produced
bathroom scale after World War Two and
anorexia so I started to see how
measures are everywhere and they
established these feedback loops and
today in a nutshell I'm where I'm
talking about is the fact that we are
witnessing the birth of the first-ever
planetary scale measurement meta
structure so it's a mouthful and
probably one of the worst titles for an
academic paper I've ever been but it's
like a very precise kind of description
of it so let me get my slides going so
this issue of planetary scale
measurement is actually quite old you
know I would argue that humans had been
trying to measure the entire world since
we became humans you know the first
attempt to build this thing which is to
say to build a measurement instrument as
big as the earth and to try to measure
the whole earth and everything on it
which is what we're trying to do with
our increasingly omniscient and
artificially intelligence enhanced
scanners and sensor networks that just
encircle the earth and uploaded all
clouds we talked about Benjamin
Bratton's notion of the planetary scale
computational stack and the first
attempt at something like that was the
Tower of Babel which you may recall was
a failed project and this is a picture
of that it was very famous so the thing
to note here which is interesting is at
the bottom of this picture you see the
king
and you see one of the workmen
addressing the Kings foot now it looks
like he is in a sense worshiping the
king what he's actually doing is getting
the measure of the Kings foot and this
in a very concrete way shows us the
relationship between measure and power
even in the ancient world and so I'm
going to trace a little bit the arc of
the conscious history of consciousness
and the evolution of measurement and the
relationship between us and to move from
anthropocentric measurement to totally
abstract geocentric measurement and back
again through this post-modernism so
we're going to get there but we start
with the Tower of Babel which is really
about this project to build a map to
basically make the planet into a giant
building and make it beautiful not
enough and tall enough to you know it's
either invite God down to hang out at
the temple or to visit him directly and
so now since then it's it's been a mess
measurement has been a problem and
measurement has been an issue of social
justice since the beginning right so
note here the archetype of justice
right what does she hold she was an
instrument of measurement and an
instrument of violence this is very
significant and seemed that we were
occurring throughout the lecture is this
relationship between measurement and
violence but also the relationship
between measurement and justice right
which is to say that true justice of the
archetype implies true justice is about
seeing objectively and about weighing
appropriately in a considered judgment
what is justice what is correct and then
of course having the sovereignty and the
power to enforce that so this is what
you're getting with this relationship
between measurement adjustments
so back to educational measurement this
is a picture of Michelle Rhee she is the
kind of infamous one-time superintendent
of the Washington DC schools and she
represents in some ways kind of the
epitome of the worst of No Child Left
Behind she used standardized tests
suggest you've got schools and fire
teachers mercilessly I mean this picture
is interesting for a number of reasons
one is that it shows directly the
relationship between measurement and
violence within a single instrument
right so what's she doing there she's
mimicking the classic school marm will
rap you on the knuckles with the ruler
right so it's something very poignant
here about the double symbolism that in
this case measurement violence are
literally United in the V are distinct
and I would say they are so in the
standardized test there's a coercion to
especially multiple-choice standardized
testing that we take for granted but in
fact it's a blunt instrument that's just
the sharp end of a stick so one way to
think about how measurement is violent
by its nature now another thing violent
is bad like surgery is violent right
self-defense could be about some forms
of science are violent so I'm not making
necessarily value judgment on violence
but what I am saying is that if we are
going to use a measurement instrument we
have to think like we're acting
surgically and not like this is a free
intervention this is actually a
measurement always does something and
this is we're gonna be returning to us
so we need to be careful what we measure
but want me to think about the nature of
violence and measurement of that it
measure allows us to impinge upon
organic form so I'm going to use an
example from architecture so this is the
city from the 1300s in Europe I believe
it's in Belgium and this city trafficked
a ton of commodities and an economic hub
and it looks actually remarkably like a
cell it looks actually very organic and
it formed very organically
and in medieval times there was mass
amounts of metrological pluralism within
Europe as a whole which is to say every
Kingdom had a different king with a
different sized foot and they use
different scales etc and so in fact this
was a place where many measures were
brought together in a centralized
marketplace the point is there was no
standardised magic now you look at
Chicago in eighteen 1852 so there's a
very different City
the only thing organic is actually the
river that's winding through it and that
river was shaped about as much as it
could be possibly by human construction
and so the idea that in fact you need to
structure it this way to run commodities
you know per unit through efficiently is
actually wrong it's been shown at some
of these old cities relatively
relatively in terms of population
traffic in just as many commodities
right so what's the logic behind
structure in Chicago this way it's very
interesting it's predicated on modern
surveying techniques and radically
standardized measures such that you know
the city blocks are identical therefore
you can lay down this many you know
sidewalks squares per block so you can
plan whole architecture whole city
escapes from hotel room based on the
standardization that was taken for
granted by 1852 much Brown now the
relationship between measurement and
violence here has to do with the fact
that the reason Chicago is structured
this way and this is an argument that's
laid out in the book called seeing like
a state which I recommend which is in
guy's last name Scott the argument here
is that structure like this actually to
quell any possibility of worker dissent
through violent uprising in this city
everyone had some legible address and
every corridor can be populated with a
police force so we can find you and we
can stop doing your buddies from getting
out of hand this was an architectural
style that was pioneered after the
French Revolution
um especially by Napoleon and it was one
of the reasons that the metric system
was actually spread throughout Europe
the metric system which is the first
example of the world centric measurement
practice but not a world centric
measurement Mehta structure we'll get to
that but the metric system was spread on
the metric system was spread around the
world on the end of the beta it's one
way to read it there's many it's very
complex history of measurement so
there's many narratives but one of them
has to do with a standardizing military
equipment and standardizing the location
of every person in the city as I
mentioned at the outset your actual
chronological age the whole measurement
logic gets turned on the human late in
modernity and into post modernity but at
first it's just a land and the commodity
production systems but what is matter
all right so this is Vermeer this is a
woman holding a balance so it's
interesting about this is actually the
picture behind her the painting within
the painting is the judgment of Christ
when he comes back right and what's
Christ holding his holding scale and a
sword and so there she stands in the
shadow of that picture holding her own
scale of course without a sword right so
the issue of where is the sovereign
behind this scale and it's actually the
burgeoning nation-state at the beginning
of the capitalist world system so but
what measurement is is a lot of things
but what we're seeing here is one of the
most practical uses of measurement
before the advances of into science
where we created measures just for the
sake of understanding things measures
were primarily created just for
practical usage so in this case she's
probably engaged in some kind of
economic transaction around the weight
of the gold and jewels
it's a pre-modern measure so I'm gonna
give a little tour here so that we don't
think measurement has a
been one thing in fact we inherit this
massive legacy of measures and those of
us innovating and the edge of
measurement technique in technology
should be aware of where this came from
and we can actually repeat terrible
missed things you know so yes so this
figure here is interesting it's a
metrological relief that they're dating
here about eighth century BC and this
would have been a common artifact on
most ancient kind of construction sites
and so what this is is it codifies the
anthropocentric dimensions of all the
key things that need to be measured
right and so this is how it began it
didn't begin with international
standards organization which I'll get to
him nor with the metric system with a
scientifically they refined length of
the meter by weight we know they were
fine the link of the meter by wavelength
of light that's how precisely this it
wasn't like that
you had unity at the work site maybe
unity at the city at best in terms of
metrological convention and then one of
the things you do if you a new ruler of
course you step in and you change it all
because that's one of the things you can
do the relation between measurement and
power is such that the rulers make the
rulers
all right so pre-modern measure looks
like that was anthropocentric and what's
so interesting about the result of the
all pre-modern measures being
anthropocentric is that there's a
certain sacred unity to all ancient
architectural sites because they all
have these similar dimensionalities
which have to do with the proportions of
human body all right so that's the
golden mean right and so you'd find
those patterns in pre-modern forms of
architecture which are actually somehow
profoundly aesthetically pleasing so as
I said we go from anthropocentric to
totally abstract geocentric and back
again what I'm saying is that the meta
modern or integral way of thinking about
measurement has to do with a return to
the human scale and a concern for
proportionalities and ratios that are
humane right because the measures of
pure abstraction allows to build
landscapes that no humans actually want
to live and allow us to build
technologies that are you know yeah a
little bit crazy because they live in
this realm of proportions and ratios
that are fiction from the perspective of
the human organism so but that's getting
ahead of ourselves priests of pre-modern
matters had a certain quality modern
measures were very different and I
talked about modern measurements
basically beginning with the metric
system
you could probably date it a little bit
earlier so this is actually a pendulum
that was specifically built and designed
by charles sanders peirce he's on my
t-shirt this is good old Charles Sanders
purse
so probably greatest philosopher you've
never heard of if you haven't heard of
them if you have and then I don't need
to say more he's kind of a legend and he
built this thing in order to see the
subtle fluctuations in the in the swing
of the pendulum due to the gravitational
field of the earth itself and this was
part of the attempts around the metric
system to figure out how being the earth
was like literally what is the
circumference of the earth many
speculations but they were actually
trying to measure the thing because they
wanted to make the meter which we all
know and love well at least you guys not
in America victory belongs to right
right so there you
but the meter was supposed to be some
specific subdivision of the actual
radius of their right so that was the
idea we don't want some kings we're
gonna make it one measure for all man
for all time was one of the chants
during the French Revolution so
understand to overthrow the ancient
regime of medieval measurement it took
the American and French Revolutions to
codify at the level of the state let
alone inter nationally it's totally
standardized reliable measures and I was
a huge actually social justice step
forward right I can go to the gas
station now regardless of what I look
like my car is what the gas station
intended thanks to me and I know I get a
gallon right and if you actually look at
the gas tank like the gas pump you'll
see there's this little thing that says
certified by the state this is a gallon
you know you can thank the French
Revolution and the call to overthrow the
arbitrary Fiat of the ruler to set the
ruler and to Institute of so-called
scientific Universal geocentric modern
measure and so that's that's modern
modern measures and modern measures as I
said were eventually turned toward the
human itself and we came to not only
desire to standardize the measurement of
land and commodity as a net cetera but
to standardize the development of humans
and so this is a fascinating artifact
from 1931 which is the standardized
service worker and this of course has
been exponential eyes labor practices in
the place like Amazon they're using
measurement techniques on they've got a
path to where was framed you know with
wrist bracelets actually track every
movement of the Amazon worker
so that's hyper measured commodified
labor so so modern measures were
eventually turned to the human and that
led to a variety of both advancements
and node attractions so eventually we
start to see beyond the pure simple
abstraction of the modern measures the
kind of monological view of modernity
and we started to get postmodern
measures that looked specifically at
what was happening
in the gaps at the dynamism at the
changes at the things that defy linear
measurement and require nonlinear ways
of thinking about how phenomena work and
so this is Jay foresters classic limits
to growth and as you can see the you
know 2100 doesn't look good and and
that's you know so this is the this is
the situation we still face this is part
of the the meta crisis but it took the
exhaustion of simple linear ways of
thinking about history and simple linear
ways of thinking about measurement in
fact to get a transition into a
dynamical systems way of thinking about
the management and one of the ways met a
monitor integral measurement moves into
the future has to do with really taking
seriously the dynamic dynamical
complexity of all phenomena such that we
never track linearly and we never do
anything like an IQ test one measurement
in a complex dynamical system you think
you know what it is that's like going in
my backyard and taking one measurement
and saying that that's how my backyard
works that's how my backward yard works
on this date this summer the winter is
very different you have to respect it by
its we have to respect what is by its
very nature unmeasurable or what demands
very complex measurement and so
postmodern measures begin to make that
turn and of course the turn towards the
human and the measuring of the human is
also deepened in post-modernism to the
point of insanity and this is actually
kind of the big warning and so notice
this one in the center says halfway
point right that means it knows where
you're going or it knows how long you
intend to run where it has some other
relationship to your value and goals
and so we measure what we care about and
we care about what we measure those two
things aren't necessarily the same which
means that you could be handed a measure
and start caring about something you
didn't care about for just because
you're measuring it now right like for
example high schoolers would never care
about their so-called scholastic
aptitude but then for about six months
also they really worried about the
amount of spastic aptitude that they
have and so similar we live in a
postmodern metrological marketplace
where there's just this rapid
proliferation of measures directed at us
and many of them are about things that
we never even heard of before and that
will the sudden there's a number and we
care about and so this is a very kind of
problematic moment I'll say gently in
the development of measurement and so
I'll say that I'll pause there and I'll
continue so what do measures do so I
would want to do was I tried to give you
let me back slide so they're not just
reading that so when I tried to show you
was that measures have evolved over time
right some things that were local an
anthropocentric
to things that are now really not and
we're really not at the scale of the
human and that's that's very important
so but all that whole stretch of things
all those things were doing roughly this
they were all measures they were all
this very different measures and so
maybe what the measures do that's one
way to think about what is a measure it
shouldn't maybe a little bit too
abstract to the question but we know
kind of what they do
measures create common sense once you
Institute a measure that's the new way
everyone relates the thing it's a shared
common sense about reality so but
they're also creations of common sense
and this is a longer discussion in
theoretical metrology about where the
measures come from it's complicated by
the end of the day they come from a
refinement are pre-existing
or intuitions so measures also serve as
shared presuppositions of cooperation
and competition so they help us to get
along but they also help us to compete
so that's important in general they are
part of what's on the table between us
right so you think about the third party
president at all human interaction
you know the symbol or the tool or the
language so a measure has that
fundamental nature it's really been part
of what humans been up to for a very
long time it's collaborating around
measures and creating new measures
that's because they mediate between the
mind and reality they're part of what
keeps us in touch with reality right
then the very first I believe in William
Irwin Thompson recorded this their first
measurement ever discovered
archaeologically it's ridiculously old
like ancient Babylonia three hundred
thousand years or something before
Christ and it was as far as we can tell
a stick used by a medicine woman to
track basically the moon and her
menstrual cycle it's just a simple notch
on a stick but what it did was and for
many the first ones were about time
which is in order to to measure it
because it's very times actually
abstract by its nature and humans relate
to time in a way animals don't and so we
needed to start keeping track of time
when we started codifying it and
mediating our relationship between our
mind and abstract objective flow of time
with this physical thing we knotch so
it's very primordial about the interest
objective relationship to reality and
I'm getting I'm just going off because I
haven't talked about this tomorrow so it
makes complexity legible but it can also
simplify complexity in a scientific
society it'll it measures legitimate
knowledge so even if you're not really
measuring something but you can kind of
produce numbers that look like you're
measuring something you have helped your
own caused by legitimating knowledge or
appearing to pretenses of objective
around measurement are very important
and that has to do
simplifying complexity so they
facilitate trust which is hugely
important that's the reason that they're
so powerful are particularly in the
history of conversations about social
justice is that and in the Bible God
says please make measures that you all
trust don't scan one another with the
measures guys because it's very
important and so this idea that it's a
it's just a locus of trust and it is
kind of one of the common part of the
Common Wealth of the community is a
trustworthy measure the only way the
community can work mm-hmm
and then of course they encode power and
this is where it gets really dicey and
there's a whole lot to say I might which
I'm probably gonna get to when we get to
the ethics part so because it's
inherently or social phenomena the issue
of who measures who always must be
raised when thinking about a measurement
now we live in a world where we take for
granted rulers and yardsticks and
gallons are all the same size but that
used to be an issue of well whose gallon
whose yardstick when you travel from one
kingdom to another for example in
medieval Europe but in general you have
to think about the way measures help
certain groups understand things that's
it if a functional utility for the most
part whether institutionalized very
practically so it's about this unequal
distribution of interpretive labour so
people who are in positions of power of
bureaucratically they don't have to
engage in interpretive labor those who
are not empowered do so reasonably this
is the tax forms rights for the tax form
it's a very complex measurement tool
used to basically determine what's going
on with you financially the onus is on
you to figure out how to fill that out
that's an example and there are other
examples this comes from a feminist
standpoint theory but in general those
people who are less in power subject to
the interpretations of those above them
and those above them are not prone to
reinterpreting
and in fact codify interpretation
through measure and so once you've
failed by standardized test doesn't
matter how it looks from your
perspective that actually that question
was weirdly worded I'm so smart I
interpreted the question differently
no ETS as you did poorly so by their
very nature that the measures are
usually held by few and effect many and
what that means is that you have these
lopsided structures and asymmetric
informational environments that last
part is key and so let's ask this bats
forward to the psychometric backends
tacked onto every website now for
advertiser right radically asymmetric
informational environment right where
few people hold the measures and many
people are affected by them just it's a
note when there are asymmetric
informational environments because
sometimes that's okay right if you have
a classroom of young students and you
have a team of teachers
it's an asymmetric information
environment it's developmentally
appropriate so a bunch of things that
make it work I think this situation with
Facebook and with those types of
asymmetric information environments
aren't that deeply problematic ethically
and it's getting worse like daily so I'm
gonna switch get here so that was kind
of like overview of a little bit of
measurement measurement history to
contextualize what's coming now and now
I'm gonna be talking about these
worldcentric futures for measurement
this is Bucky Fuller's Dymaxion map
which if you don't know about you should
totally check it out so I already
mentioned Benjamin Britten's notion of
this planetary scale computational stack
and so is this intriguing but very in
fact once your reader like oh of course
this is what's happening right that the
earth is being encircled in a giant mega
structure that is essentially a computer
and and the most important thing to
realize about tests is that it's
accidental and he uses that phrase
repeatedly accidental planetary
computational stack and
you have to get that like I chicken rut
who's at the Santa Fe Institute once
said like evolutionarily speaking you
can understand a lot of human behavior
by realizing that humans are the
stupidest animals capable of culture
it's like least a viable product culture
like humans are the stupidest possible
animals culture right now we are the
stupidest the possible culture capable
of generating a planetary computational
stack and therefore also the stupidest
possible culture capable of generating
something within that stack which is a
planetary measurement meta structure
which is the measurement or description
of the stack through the measures within
it very recursive but the fact that it's
an accidental planetary measurement meta
structure should give us all some
concern and so that's kind of like it
ended there I mean this is so you leave
this whole history of measurement you
realize a relationship to a measurement
power you realize the relationship
between measurement in reality we're
measuring community measurement justice
and then you realize for the first time
we've locked in accidentally a planetary
measurement member structure that as we
saw with Apple watch goes right to your
skin and they're making pills that you
can swallow pharmaceutical companies
that have a microchip in them that is
sure that you're taking your meds but
what they do is they link the planetary
computational meta structure directly
into your stomach and so and this is all
unfolding historically in a time period
when less than 200 years ago we didn't
know our own ages by numerical
quantification so we've gone from a
relatively unmeasured species to
erratically or hyper measured species
extremely rapidly so that means that we
need to sit back and think very
seriously about measurements again in
the ancient world we thought a lot about
measuring Aristotle is politics he
collected he claims all the
Constitution's
from all over the ancient world of
course lost with the library of
Alexander burning down but Aristotle
claims that no and we look into what he
writes about summarizing these and you
realize that right front and center in
the Constitution's of the ancient world
were meta theoretical concerns about
management right who gets to decide how
much is a sack corn right the Miller or
the farmer etc and so we've been running
on the success of the metric system as
if everything we measure turned to gold
and ought to be measured in fact right
now we need to pause and think very
deeply about a whole domain of things
that we should maybe never measure
that's one of my claims that in fact a
meta modern approach to measurement
respects the immeasurable and partitions
off regions that are not to be measured
now and that comes from understanding
what it means to measure something so
this gets into the meta theory of
measurement and so I'm thrilled that you
guys have already had an introduction to
Wilbur to a certain extent and the
integral metatheory that he created with
these quadrants which in fact retrofit a
perennial set of deep men of theoretical
distinctions and so when it comes to
measurement any measurement instance can
be an ought to be thought of in terms of
these quadrants this is a simple way to
do a thought experiment about what's
really unfolding as a measure is
instituted what what's really happening
here all measures actually have a
subjective meaning attached to them
right so from one perspective the SAT
score is just in a projective index
of your scholastic aptitude but of
course on the interior of the individual
it is has a whole ton of significance
about their future and there are
self-esteem and all these other things
so any measurement instance can be
analyzed from a perspective of is it
ethical or just right you can also think
about the objectivity and the efficiency
enabled by the measure so if you think
about this most of what we talk about
when we talk about measurement is the
right hand quadrant stuff we talk about
is the measure objective and does the
measure enable efficiency right so if
you were trying to for example I don't
know
you know distort an election and you
were trying to target ads specifically
to people who had certain psychological
profiles you'd want to know are we
accurately detecting these classes are
they real classes are we objectively
doing this well and are we doing it in
efficient let's say like a race seeding
and doing that you can do all of that
still be doing psychological measurement
paying entirely out of the right-hand
quadrant not worrying about the ethics
or the impact on the subjective life for
those people right so once you start to
factor all of these things that's when
you start to realize oh we should not
measure some stuff and so when you hear
people speak especially about the
blockchain you realize that there's
actually this strange to use biblical
language kind of hubris or demonic
impulse to create a totally omniscient
meta structure formation right like this
is odd I hear people who have no
authoritarian leanings at all but who
want to track every transaction and
every gesture and even like your own
mindfulness and good actions towards
your mom and stuff they want to log at
all in watching Wow seems
epistemologically quite greedy to me and
also like you're trying to sit on the
throne a
judgment and so so we should think about
this ideal this implicit and
unarticulated ideal of an entire time
the ammunition measurement meta
structure of planetary scale this is
actually one of those things that is
kind of bad infinity the bag alien sense
it's like a fallen angel the nitrogen
sense so if the Archangel Metatron were
to run the way of Lucifer you would end
up with an entirely omniscient
inescapable ash from the meta structure
of planetary scale right and Metatron if
you don't know he's ascended was Enoch
Methuselah Noah's grandfather
ended up turning into Archangel he's the
only one who can sit next to God because
his job is to dictate everything
that happens and to map out the entire
body of God that's been manifest in
small and so it's heavy job measurement
intensive practice we developed
measuring all of the material world but
of course that's an archetype and an
ideal and to imagine bringing that into
physical reality and making a truly
Amish measurement method of structure
that's an example of something humans
get chained to rocks and then these
birds eat out their livers
you know the idea that you shouldn't fly
too close to the Sun and etc so this is
humors there's also irrational doesn't
hold together logically it's very easy
to take apart the idea and realize that
it is possible so for example would it
map itself would an omniscient
measurement meta structure map its own
turn own it would have to map its own
internal architecture for self
regulation purposes so there are logical
flaws within the very ideal itself which
is another thing that ideals have they
are often paradoxical so then the
question becomes how do we you know in
an appropriate way limit the omniscient
was the principled way to rein in what
we could do because I'm not saying it's
impossible no but I'm asking it's
impossible I'm saying we shouldn't do
it's very different there's a lot of
things in artificial intelligence that
are that way too
it's not that they are impossible it's
that they shouldn't be done
and this is not a way that we're used to
thinking but it's a way that we have to
start to think because of the power that
we have now and the accidental
measurement Mehta structure is like an
atomic bomb in our hands in terms of the
devastation that it could yield and yeah
so that's you know me to think so how do
we limit it could measure everything we
could make your life every gesture every
speech act it could be measured and
logged in the cloud so what do we not
measure so another reminder you know
that the Internet of Things is also if
not primarily an Internet of people and
so most of the sensor networks and even
most of the things that tracks truly
physical properties that don't do
semantic analysis or anything most of
those things are used to track human
behavior or human desire you can tell a
lot about some of them by the physical
things that are mailed to their house so
here's the idea integral measurement
praxis and this slide contains a lot and
it's essentially unchanged from my 2015
side and summarizes what's in the paper
that's coming out in the book and so one
of the things that characterizes this
kind of measurement practice which also
characterizes meta modern and the reason
it's meta modern is because it takes
both modern and postmodern moves very
seriously
we're not dismissing them and saying
let's go back to the ancient ways that's
impossible first of all that is
something that's impossible
because time travel is impossible but
it's also just not the right way to even
hold yourself in your in your being you
need to think about a future that has
the best of what modernity did and
remember the metric system overthrew the
ancient regime which was exploiting
people through the arbitrary Fiat of
each ruler just set the ruler right that
was overthrown now everyone gets the
same all right that's a huge move
forward so we can't and that
post-modernism can
that step forward they can forget what
was boone about universalism when it was
overthrowing medievalism but then of
course it petrified and expanded beyond
human proportions
and so post-modernism reminds us about
the limits of abstract measurement but
post-modernism has proliferated the
measurement of the human and in fact
diced us up into a thousand fragmented
sub personalities and kind of
commodified kind of market demographics
which were fed you know through our
screens and so I'm proposing that we
actually instead of thinking about what
we are measuring which is what we know
how to do that those people who are
concerned with measurement and creative
creation of new measures need to think
about the non ecology of absence this is
the work of Roy best artists we need to
go for this result of thing about
absence which it means every time you
measure something you have to think
about what you left out so respect not
just what can't be measured technically
but respect even when you're measuring
what you haven't measured by virtue of
measuring it that's important when I
measure the length of a table haven't
waited so let me know it I've measured
the length not the way when I measure
the IQ of someone I haven't measured a
lot of other stuff to say that I've
measured this but I haven't measured
boom boom boom window linger on the
absences right that actually frame the
presence of your finding when you
measure okay you don't see it unless
you're ignoring something else that's
actually our measurement works
measurement simplifies complexity by
showing you this at the expense of that
so so the men about our move is to say I
see this but I'm aware of that right and
that is especially when you're treating
humans
it's just respectful that's why as a
dyslexic I appreciated the special
educators who said oh yeah the SAT
measures this but it doesn't measure
these and other things that you're good
which is true and it doesn't mean yet
too
who proved the SAT which you can which
I'd love to do you don't have to you can
just say yeah it's true but partial and
every single measure is true but partial
you have to think that way and so as I
said you need to respect the
immeasurable presents the unmeasured
allow for uniqueness and uniqueness is
actually very technical from a
metrological perspective and uniqueness
is an undeniable ontological facet of
every entity and therefore if you can't
find uniqueness with your measure then
the whole purpose of your measures to
destroy uniqueness most measures in
pinja pond or specifically or designed
to give the uniqueness out and focus on
what everything hasn't common but if you
throw enough measures at something over
a long enough time scale you can find
they unique even in the universal that's
what dynamic systems modeling does so
everything has a temperature but not
everything has this temperature
signature which is a temporarily
unfolding fluctuation of temperatures
which can only be measured over multiple
measurements is over time right so
that's a way to use the universal to
detect the unique and not use the
universal to detect one of three right
not use the universal to detect one and
seven use the universal to detect the
unique very different and actually a
huge challenge even for the most gifted
educators and basically at this point
impossible from the perspective of
design technologically so that's another
conversation so I've talked about the
dynamical systems but but we have to
think of the planetary stack as resting
on a cloud not on a rock
the reality of human culture is
consistently changing the reality of
each mind is so much flux and dynamism
that if we imagine the stack resting on
some piece of like manipulable rock or
clay or blank slate we're gonna do some
damage because we're going to force
we're gonna force things into that mold
so we need to assume as much dynamism as
there could possibly be and then working
to kind more so that's about again
privileged in the dynamical perspective
first then going to the linear it's
necessary not starting with the linear
and then going to the dynamical when you
realize that the linear model doesn't
apply you see so it's it's actually
making good on the paradigm change to
the dynamical systems modeling that was
you know prophesized in the seventies
and then finally the interiors and
ethics and aesthetics as part of
measurement conversation to expand what
it means to be an expert in discourse
was about measurement and so right now
again remember a symmetries of
informational environments and the
rulers make the ruler so right now most
of the conversations about the future of
the planetary measurement meta structure
are happening in backrooms among experts
and not necessarily because they are
like a conspiratorial because precisely
because they're experts that no one
actually nope it was started to be about
in those times so with the so the when
you do is open these conversations to
realize their human significance and
again start thinking about the ratios
and the scales and the relationships
between utility and efficiency and
meaning and ethics that's where the main
tension is the primary driver of modern
and in many ways the postmodern is
efficiency over ethics notice oh we need
to reverse that which means we actually
need to worry about what's unique and
what's inefficient
god forbid and non unsustainable or
stupid but not reductionistic Li and
mechanistically efficient which is what
we'd like to see the educational system
be for example so that's the talk I kind
of really kind of went for it and like I
said I haven't been talking about this
much lately
and I didn't know exactly what I was
gonna say and you know I think I've
probably raised more questions for you
guys then I have and this was extremely
provisional and in fact while I don't
regret saying anything in particular I
do have a vague sense that I didn't say
a bunch of important stuff that I should
have said no I'm hoping that you have
some questions and that we'll find that
stuff I mean that's that's exactly the
type of measure that I think needs to be
talked about so I'm really glad you
raised that and so sure you guys are
aware that there's a huge burgeoning
academic field around measuring things
like happiness wellness these things and
so what I'm gonna do is talk about how I
would approach evaluating those measures
of thinking about those measures as far
as whether it should be measured or not
I think
since that train has left the station
right like I don't think we kind of shut
that industry down as it were and let's
stop the drilling you know what I mean I
don't know that we're because it seems
no one face value like we should be
thinking about least for research
purposes so here's some of the stuff
that's on my mind fed right so
definitionally well-being is a
philosophical problem sorry for my
french so that's the first right are we
taking seriously the complexity of what
it means to have well be the provisional
studies in happiness show at people who
often on the short-term are unhappy
that's for example like two young
children lives are if you were like how
you feeling about how tired oh
my god and like over the long run they
express these deeper more profound
senses right which people who are happy
day to day often have these lingering
existential kind of doubts about the
future significance that's not about is
one happy you're not happy that's that's
about how complex the concept of
happiness and well-being is at least as
complex and so what we need to do is be
very careful warmer thinking about this
to be sure that we are not codify some
superficial definition right that's kind
of like it's socially acceptable and
useful for people to be exploited that's
that's my sense like there was a town in
Louisiana that was declared to be the
happiest town in America
it's just because they have grades all
day and it was full of basically very
conservative Christians so yes happiest
town America right this is it about the
definitional first steps that means
who's behind the research and the
funding matter who's measuring who's
deciding go ask the healthcare companies
who's deciding what well-being is they
decide that's good for you that's not so
when you look at the fringes of what's
acceptable in medicine you start to say
oh yeah
actually they're details in that
question in general you can see them a
little bit skeptical of the current work
because most but I'm also thinking about
that we live in a time when certain
definitions of well-being could be
what's actually taking place so that's
mostly I see these conversations no
which is to say I want to get too
radical but my sense is that there are
certain historical moments in which well
you're not paying attention
in one sense right and so if we're
throwing measures of happiness at a
population and demonstrating back to
them oh your goods are actually happy
they may not feel like it but you're
actually out on the whole you're happy
they're just like all these people
you're not sitting they're actually
happy we prove that this is Galen
that's a very weird and nefarious that's
right and again you know mmm
like what are you doing with the measure
are you trying to get a press release
like and that's again who's measuring
who for what purpose
where's this being codified into a
technology that's giving them feedback
to improve their so that's a lot of the
measurement things are done so write
papers to argue how healthy our society
so alright I could keep rambling there
so I haven't answered your question
intentionally I've just said here's what
I think about these things if I were to
approach it
I wouldn't it would be not something you
can not work out in a napkin
this is we nassif really deeply and we
would actually end up being I think a
politically radical radical project if
you really figure out how to measure
some aspect of human interior already
you realize that live in a culture that
is decimating humanity reorders you can
really measure learning
one of the big things we're developing
is a UTI or social architecture that
allows users to in people just hear the
feedback of themselves and their belief
constructs and systems to the AI rather
than new feds will eat that and in that
way we're looking at what data we need
to be backed users to love the Emir of
roses and how do you this video the
system to do it by a known population
data and relational data or give up some
user centric decentralized kind of tag
to a larger pool how would you approach
something like that yeah great question
because there's a lot of these kinds of
things kind of emerging and so I'm of
the school that believes you should
always put the measurement tools in the
users hands I don't think that it should
come from
and a curtain like tada did this magical
stuff back here and then tada
like that's the right approach you need
to let them see how it works and as much
as possible let them actually configure
and play with the assessment themselves
that's good for two reasons one is that
you'll end up with a better assessment
system because whatever your team sizes
and the other one is that it empowers as
opposed to so again any measurement
instance is it's actually a political
relationship of power it's not a
scientific relationship of objective
it's not immoral or non relationship
that's just two people hanging out
sometimes it is a always a political on
the street and I was approaching this
guy what would I do
I probably like put a table between us
and show him what I was gonna do to him
first
ancient polar not aged in medieval
Poland if you were to measure Somoza to
hexyl but you weren't allowed to measure
people and in fact sometimes doctors
would come in when you're sick and all
they would do is measure you and and
people get better
I mean sometimes obviously they're
probably diagnosed at the time but is
very vague which is that as much as
possible empower the person who's being
measured they're being measured and
actually to be able to augment the
measure so it's like if you have a
mirror and you want to be able to can
you clean the mirror oh I want to get
dis angle I want to get that angle you
know what I mean so they can you turn
the mirror around to get that magnifying
mirror Oh buddy check back because you
know actually you don't let the night
fine they're like you want to have that
capability for them and then they feel
like they're not some test subject and
they're not subject to some magical
assessment they don't understand in fact
they see what's going on
and it's part of their tool kit and so
that that would be in general my
response I think there is a potential to
do what you're doing in a way that's
quite quite bad for people because for
example the AI comes back and gives them
some world view that kind of doesn't
really fit with what they thought about
themselves that's weird
who do I believe right the magical AI
who was designed by all these fancy
people all this money and I don't know
how it works and but it says that you
know like hell with that big red like
you are actually a nihilist who do you
believe like you want them to know how
this assessment work so that when they
give the results like okay this this
makes sense and so that means also a
general thing is that as much as
possible you want constructive responses
not selected response right and
constructive response
shouldn't be confused with just semantic
coding fruit writing necessarily a
constructive response this is a deeper
question psychometric so just because
you're tracking when someone writes
doesn't mean that you've given them
actually a selected response item to
work of course multiple-choice we all
know is bad although a lot of people
still use noise but many forms semantic
analysis are just a really complicated
question and they're filling in the
bubbles by writing certain words I just
don't realize truly constructive
response is one that looks at the
argumentation and the reasoning it's
actually much harder to do with
intelligence if not impossible so what
that means is that again by uniqueness
right
how many world believes you got because
I got an endless variety of world and so
the question is what is the
classification scheme that's ultimately
being produced and does the
classification scheme allow for the
representation of uniqueness which is to
say that every person who took it could
get a different score not every person
who takes it gets class into one of
eight categories or 120 or one of a
hundred or one of a thousand each person
gets a difference for again you can do
this if you're doing complex measuring
over time right every tree in my
backyard I tracked it with enough
instruments which worked differently
period every humans the same way so if
you're coming short of that and you're
building the measure for some specific
instrumental reason you have to think
about why you're doing and so that's my
other like hard stop with all project is
like there's a conceptual issue with the
idea of worldview and that you could put
me in a worldview man like try it like
it's a fancy artificial intelligence but
do we really want to start telling
people that they fit in one of 10 or 100
of 20 I don't know that's an open
philosophical question that a
philosopher of Education it's been a
long time worrying about
which people are going on in doing just
great but again this is unprecedented
territory we've never had a machine that
told us things about ourselves we didn't
know about ourselves kriesel we used to
do that eventually the computational
stack could become some kind of
artificial intelligent demigod that
knows us better than we know ourselves
and we trusted and it measures and not
physically in the room with you it's
easy for me to be honest I think it's
too I think it's I think it's it's too
late for Facebook that's like that's
like to corrupt ancient regime like all
that should we're using to surveil you
and exploit you and all that stuff now
you can use these are the masters tools
man like they were used to exploit into
trick and to commodify and to surveil
and to manipulate without consent
and the idea that we can now now but we
have access to them now it's all cool
guys not at all not at all I don't know
what's to be done
in fact like I said it's an
unprecedented situation and I don't
think again we have the tools to deal
with a lot of the ethical problems that
we face and this is wonderful and yeah
so again I think some kind of open
platform the Galit arianism that allows
people to build something like Facebook
might be interesting the question of
whether people are even interested now
because the damage has been done and
they'd rather just stick with Facebook
and make do sounds a lot like what we've
been doing with capitalism for the past
34 years I don't think there's much time
left
and so I actively worked to tell people
to get off Facebook so I record you to
do that for exactly the reasons I've
just been discussing so I you know the
idea of fixing it is like the idea of
fixing the public schools to me it's
like no you know we need to something
profoundly different so I'm profoundly
new and measurement is part of the
reason why I so it's not I mean it's not
a happy answer I think actually in fact
the possibility of pivoting towards some
type of infrastructure that has many of
the affordances of Facebook even
psychometrically for self-reflection is
huge so one way to think about it is
like the nuclear power plant that came
from the Manhattan Project all right the
bad guys built all of this stuff but
there are humane uses for it right but
we have to take it off the military base
and literally with Facebook military
base and bring it to a place where the
citizens can look at what's available
some find some kind of agreement about
how to use this incredibly powerful for
you know relationship and
measurement and again so it may be that
we decide that we don't want to do
something like this again after the and
again I'm I'm predicting not a happy
future if the state of the internet and
the informational you go system remains
as it is the egg is symmetric
informational environments alone coupled
with economic inequality assure massive
rest it's not just that they're richer
it's that they're smarter and they know
stuff about us that we don't even know
you know that's a bad recipe and so yeah
so I think an alternative one needs to
start to be being built not work within
the old one but start to really start to
build something different and people
will talk to it you know Bucky fuller
you have to build the alternative so
that would be my sense and from whole
from scratch you know with lessons
learned again we were the stupidest
possible specie to build a social
networking site species anymore right we
can learn a lesson getting the body
language to start
thank you guys